Diego Grados

As a bioscience engineer, agroecologist and applied statistician, my work is centered on solving sustainable development challenges in agriculture. I use interdisciplinary approaches focusing on the fundamental and applied aspects of soil-plant-atmosphere interactions, agroecosystem analysis and remote sensing. With extensive involvement in international research projects alongside multidisciplinary partners, I have honed my teamwork and communication skills. I am proficient in programming languages for data-processing applications and processbased modelling. Additionally, I am enthusiastic about creating integrated assessments that use data science to translate information into knowledge.

Personal Data

diegogradosb@agro.au.dk ResearchID Email GYR-1584-2022 https://diegogradosb.github.io ORCID 0000-0001-5548-3204

Relevant Experience

SEP 2020 -**PRESENT**

Postdoctoral Researcher - AARHUS UNIVERSITY, Aarhus - Denmark

Climate and Water - Agroecology Department - Faculty of Technical Sciences

- Study of mitigation strategies for greenhouse gas emissions and adaptation practices to climate change. International and national collaboration projects: PROENV, MACSUR SciPol, ZERO, KlimaGødning.
- Dissemination of results in seminars, workshops, peer-reviewed journals and international conferences.
- Supervision of MSc and PhD thesis students.

Reference: Prof. Dr. Diego ABALOS, Prof. Dr. Jørgen Eivind OLESEN

JUL 2023 -AGO 2023 Visiting Researcher - MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (Faculty of Climate, Environment and Life Science) and Boston College (Faculty of Earth and Environmental Sciences), Massachusetts - United States of America

- Collaboration on using machine-learning techniques and the terrestrial biosphere model (DLEM) to assess nitrogen cycling and crop production from agroecosystems at global scale.

Reference: Prof. Dr. César TERRER, Prof. Dr. Hanqin TIAN

Nov 2021 -**DEC 2021**

Visiting Researcher - KARLSRUHE INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, Garmisch-Partenkirchen - Germany Institute of Meteorology and Climate Research, Atmospheric Environmental Research

- Collaboration on using the LandscapeDNDC terrestrial ecosystem model to simulate greenhouse gas emissions and crop production at site and regional scale.

Reference: Dr. Edwin Haas, Prof. Dr. Klaus Butterbach-Bahl

JAN 2020 -

Researcher - KU LEUVEN, Leuven - Belgium

MAR 2020

Biostatistics and Sustainability Groups - Biosystems Department - Faculty of Bioscience Engineering

APR 2016 -

PhD Researcher - KU LEUVEN, Leuven - Belgium

DEC 2019

- Developing multi-target and system modeling methodologies for the agroecosystems' sustainability assessment.
- Dissemination of results in seminars, workshops, peer-reviewed journals and international conferences.
- Supervision of BSc and MSc thesis students in Peru (UNALM and UNCP) and Belgium (KU Leuven).

Reference: Prof. Dr. Eddie SCHREVENS

Nov 2014 -APR 2019

Research Assistant - VLIR/UOS PROJECT, Lima - Peru

Strengthening of Smallholder Horticultural Systems Subproject

- Co-leading the study of soil-plant-atmosphere interactions in the Peruvian Coastal Desert.
- Installation of soil, meteorological and irrigation equipment.
- Design, installation and analysis of agricultural experiments under drip irrigation systems. Reference: Prof. Dr. Eddie Schrevens, Prof. Dr. Guido Wyseure, Prof. Dr. Jan Diels

SEP 2013 -**DEC 2018**

Research Officer - VLIR/UOS PROJECT, Junin - Peru

Sustainable Agriculture in the Central Peruvian Andes Subproject

- Lead the design, installation and evaluation of agricultural experiments under rainfed conditions.
- Consolidation of rational databases, development of soil-plant-atmosphere models and statistical techniques. - Analysis of agroecosystems using participatory approaches along with biophysical and biochemical assessments.

Reference: Prof. Dr. Eddie Schrevens, Prof. Dr. Sady García

FEB 2013 -APR 2019

Research Officer - VLIR/UOS PROJECT, Junin | Lima - Peru

Drone Technology in Agriculture Subproject

- Lead the feasibility study for uses of drone technology in agroecosystems.
- In charge of drone flights in Peruvian's Andes and Arid regions. Implementation of photogrammetric and GIS databases.
- Development of mathematical and statistical workflows for land use classification and field experiments' assessment.

Reference: Prof. Dr. Eddie Schrevens, Sr. R&D Dries Raymaekers

JAN 2012 -**DEC 2018**

Research Officer - VLIR/UOS PROJECT, Junin - Peru

Watersheds Management Subproject

- $\hbox{-} \ Lead the study of soil-plant-atmosphere interactions and hydrology in the Peruvian Central Andes. \\$
- Installation of soil, climatological and hydrometric equipment.
- $Implementation \ of \ databases, \ application \ of \ hydrological \ models \ and \ assessment \ of \ rainfall-runoff \ relations.$

Reference: Prof. Dr. Eduardo Chávarri, Prof. Dr. Guido Wyseure

Education

APR 2016 -PhD in Bioscience Engineering, Biostatistics and Sustainability - KU Leuven, Belgium

DEC 2019 Thesis Title: "Multi-target methodologies for the improvement of agricultural systems research

- Study cases at system and field level". | Advisor: Prof. Dr. Eddie Schrevens

Jan 2007 -DEC 2011

BSc in Agricultural Engineering, Hydrology - Agrarian National University La Molina, Peru Honor Thesis Title: "Analysis of flood peaks in small Andean watersheds, Junin Department,

Peru (2011-2012 Period)". | Advisor: Prof. Dr. Eduardo Chávarri

Relevant Publications

- 1. **Grados, D.**, Butterbach-Bahl, K., Chen, J., Van Groenigen, K. J., Olesen, J., Van Groenigen, J. W., Abalos, D., 2022. Synthesizing the evidence of nitrous oxide mitigation practices in agroecosystems. *Environmental Research Letters*. https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ac9b50.
- 2. **Grados, D.**, Reynafarje, X., Schrevens, E., 2020. A methodological approach to assess canopy NDVI–based tomato dynamics under irrigation treatments. *Agricultural Water Management*, 240, 106208. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agwat.2020.106208.
- 3. **Grados, D.,** García, S., Schrevens, E., 2020. Assessing the potato yield gap in the Peruvian Central Andes. *Agricultural Systems*, 181, 102817. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agsy.2020.102817.
- 4. **Grados, D.,** Schrevens, E., 2019. Multidimensional analysis of environmental impacts from potato agricultural production in the Peruvian Central Andes. *Science of The Total Environment*, 663, 927–934. http://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.01.414.

Relevant Conference Proceedings [PEER-REVIEWED]

- Grados, D., García, S., Schrevens, E., Nitrogen and water use efficiency under rain-fed potato agriculture: An experimental study. *Acta Horticulturae* (1253, 243–252). *International Symposium on Water and Nutrient Relations and Management of Horticultural Crops*, Istanbul, Turkey, 12-16 Aug 2018. http://doi.org/10.17660/actahortic.2019.1253.33.
- Grados, D., Vetters, E., Heuts, R., Schrevens, E., A model based technical sustainability analysis of potato production systems in the Mantaro Valley, Central Highlands, Peru. *Acta Horticulturae (1154, 155-152). Symposium on Applications of Modelling as an Innovative Technology in the Horticultural Supply Chain*, Wageningen, The Netherlands, 11-14 Oct 2015. http://doi.org/10.17660/actahortic. 2017.1154.20.
- Grados, D., Vera, J., Schrevens, E., Corn-faba bean associations in the Peruvian Central Andes. *Acta Horticulturae* (1128, 79-88). *International Symposium on Horticulture in Developing Countries and World Food Production*, Brisbane, Australia, 19-22 Aug 2014. http://doi.org/10.17660/actahortic.2016. 1128.11.

Teaching Experience

- FA 2021 Carbon Cycling and Climate Change Master in Agrobiology, Aarhus University
 - Teacher Assistant: I lectured on soil nitrogen cycling and nitrous oxide emissions. I guided students during the discussion and practical sessions to assess agroecosystems. I supported them on the development of their research papers. [20 students]
- FA 2017 Applied Multivariate Statistical Analysis Master in Bioscience Engineering, KU Leuven
 - Teacher Assistant: I taught students how to analyze their databases using statistical software by leading R-tutorials. I was responsible for the practical sessions on data wrangling and visualization, matrix algebra, R-programming and advanced multivariate techniques. [80 students]
- FA 2019 Biological Production Systems Bachelor in Bioscience Engineering, **KU Leuven**Teacher Assistant: I guided students during discussions and practical sessions to assess agroecosystems.

 I taught them the essentials of process-based mathematical modelling and supported them on the development of their research papers. [25 students]
- SP 2016 Ecosystems Modelling Master in Bioscience Engineering, **KU Leuven**Teacher Assistant: I taught students how to develop and utilize ecosystems models at diverse scales by leading R-tutorials. I guided the practical sessions on mathematical and statistical concepts, data wrangling and visualization, R-programming. I taught them the fundamental topics on process-based modelling of ecosystems: identification, implementation, calibration and validation. [10 students]

Fellowships and Grants

- 2023 Land-CRAFT Research Grant [6 000€]
- 2022 Aarhus University Travel Grant [400€]
- 2021 iClimate Research Grant [3 600€]
- 2020 **FONDECYT-CONCYTEC** Research Grant [5 500€]
- 2016 2019 **VLIR/UOS** PhD Fellowship [82 000€]
- 2013 | 2014 | 2015 VLIR/UOS International Scholar Fellowships [67 000€]

Ad-Hoc Reviewer

Agronomy for Sustainable Development, Agricultural Systems, European Journal of Agronomy, European Journal of Soil Science, Geoderma, Journal of Cleaner Production, Plant and Soil, Soil Use and Management, Theoretical and Applied Climatology.

Languages

English: Full professional proficiency
French: Limited working proficiency
Spanish: Native/Bilingual

Technical Skills

Programming: R, Python
Markup: Markdown, LTE

Other: RStudio, Spyder, Office, QGIS, ArcGIS, Git/GitHub, HTML/CSS, HPC, Open Science Framework,

Adobe Illustrator